Guide to the Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975:Personal papers, 1937-2016, bulk 1967-1981 MS2392
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Madeleine Golde papers, 1937-1981; 1967-1981; Series 4
  - Local 41 Discrimination Hearing [American Federation of Government Employees ], 1972; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Local 41 Leaflets AFGE [American Federation of Government Employees ], Circa 1971; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - AFGE [American Federation of Government Employees ] Local 41 Collective Bargaining, 1973; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - AFGE [American Federation of Government Employees ]Rank and File Organization, 1972; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - AFGE [American Federation of Government Employees ] National Convention – 1972, Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Hatch Act and Conduct Regulations, Circa 1966-1968; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - CLUW [Coalition of Labor Union Women] Founding Convention, 1974; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - CLUW NCC [Coalition of Labor Union Women National Coordinating Committee]– Chicago 1974, 1974 Steptember; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - CLUW [Coalition of Labor Union Women] Newspaper Clippings, 1974; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - CLUW [Coalition of Labor Union Women] Newsletters, 1974-1977; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - CLUW [Coalition of Labor Union Women] Recruitment, Circa 1974; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - CLUW [Coalition of Labor Union Women] Other Chapters, 1975; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - CLUW [Coalition of Labor Union Women] Steering Committee Minutes, 1975; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - CLUW [Coalition of Labor Union Women] Programs, 1975; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - CLUW NCC [Coalition of Labor Union Women National Coordinating Committee] Meeting Houston 1975, 1975 June; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - CLUW NCC [Coalition of Labor Union Women National Coordinating Committee] Meeting St. Louis 1975, Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - CLUW NCC [Coalition of Labor Union Women National Coordinating Committee] Constitution and Bylaws Committee, 1975; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - CLUW [Coalition of Labor Union Women] March 8 – International Women's Day, 1975 March; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - CLUW [Coalition of Labor Union Women] Minutes of D.C. Meetings 1974-75, 1975; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - CLUW [Coalition of Labor Union Women] General, 1974-1975; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - CLUW [Coalition of Labor Union Women] Membership, Circa 1975; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - CLUW [Coalition of Labor Union Women] Constitutional Convention – Detroit 1975, 1975 December; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Federal Employees Vietnam Moratorium – Oct. 15, 1969, Series 4 (Map-folder 1, Item 1)
- John Hanrahan papers, 1965-2016; 1968-1988; Series 5
  John Hanrahan is a former Washington Post reporter/union activist in support of 1975 pressmen's strike at the Post; also a DC community activist on voting rights, other local issues.
  This series contains materials related to the D.C. Statehood Movement. The subjects and people include many key local activists of the 1960s-1970s such as Julius Hobson, Hilda Mason, Charles Mason, Josephine (Jo) Butler, Sammie Abbott, Brint Dillingham,, Selma Rein; Anti-War Demonstrations; Anti-Freeway Fight; Civil rights, and extensive coverage of the Washington Post Pressmen's Strike years 1975-1977.
  John Hanrahan was a participant in the Lessons of the Sixties oral history project. The interview is part of collection MS2388. Listen to the interview..
  - D.C. Statehood Movement, Circa 1980; Series 5 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - D.C. Statehood Movement, Circa 1980; Series 5 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - D.C. Statehood Movement, Circa 1980; Series 5 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - D.C. Statehood Movement, Circa 1980; Series 5 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - D.C. Statehood Movement, Circa 1980; Series 5 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Statehood, Circa 1980-2016; Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Hearing S.J. Res 65 Statehood, 1978; Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Freeway, 2013; Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Underground Newspapers, Circa 1967-1971; Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Underground newspapers, Washington Free Press, Quicksilver Times
  - March on Washington, Vietnam, Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Keywords provided by the donor: 1965 March on Washington, 11/27/65, SANE
  - Sam Abbott, Circa 1984-2013; Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Sam Abbott, Freeway fight leader
  - Angela Rooney, 1972; Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Angela Rooney, Freeway fight leader
  - 1960s Miscellaneous Articles, Circa 1960s; Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Vietnam War, Civil Rights, Senator J.W. Fulbright's speeches and statements – Militarism and Vietnam, Ramparts Magazine issues – Mississippi and Che Guevara, Articles on "Young Radicals"
  - 1960s Miscellaneous Articles, 1968-2013; Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - ACCESS (Action Coordinating Committee to End Segregation in the Suburbs), 1966; Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    Keywords provided by the donor: ACCESS (Action Coordinating Committee to End Segregation in the Suburbs)
  - Peoples Coalition for Peace and Justice/May Day 1971 -- April 24-May 5, 1971, 1971 April 24 - May 05; Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Peoples Coalition for Peace and Justice/May Day 1971 -- April 24-May 5, 1971
  - Brint Dillingham, Undated; Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Brint Dillingham (J. Brinton Dillingham)
  - Joseph Forer, Selma and David Rein, 1986-1987; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Selma Samols
  - Selma - Samols, Circa 1986; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Josephine Butler
  - Josephine Butler, 1979; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Julius Hobson
  - Julius Hobson, Circa 1982; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Keywords provided by the donor: COINTELPRO, FBI/DC police spying on local Black Antiwar activists
  - COINTELPRO, 1986-2016; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Al McSurely, Margaret McSurely (Herring)
  - Al McSurely/Margaret McSurely (Herring), Circa 1972; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters, press releases, pamphlets (general, Circa 1976; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Alternative press reporting, Circa 1975-1977; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Alternative reporting, 1976-1977; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Harvard Business School case study, Circa 1975-1977; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Letters, 1975-1976; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Letters, 1975-1977; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - legal documents [pressman strike], 1975-1976; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Washington Post Pressman's strike. Local 6, Newspaper Guild
  - Photos [Washington Post strike], undated; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Hanrahan et al analysis [Washington Post strike], circa 2015; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Official statements [Washington Post strike], 1976; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Magazine articles, 1975-1988; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Mainstream reporting, 1976; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Mainstream reporting, 1975-1976; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Rank/file stike support committee, 1975-1977; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Radio TV coverage of the strike, 1975-1976; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Miscelaneious [Washington Post strike], 1975-1977; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Newsletters, press releases, pamphlets (general, Circa 1976; Series 5 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Giles Brothers Case, 1965-1979; Series 5 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Giles Brothers Case, Harold Knapp, citizens support group, Joe Forer attorney
  - Hilda and Charles Mason, Circa 2007; Series 5 (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Norman Oslik papers, Circa 1970-1977; Series 6
  Norman Oslik's first activism began when he joined the Vietnam Moritorium Committee at NIH/NIMH in 1970 as part of his growing opposition to the war in Vietnam. During this period he also worked on various labor and community issues with the Alliance for Labor and Community Action, including helping to publish a community newsletter, supporting workers in various labor conflicts and working on the Alliance's Unemployment Committee. Over the next several decades he has continued his activism in a variety of arenas, including local environmental protection issues, community involvement in local development projects, and union organizing as well as serving for six years as an elected Town Council Member.
  This series covers Norman Oslik's work in the anti-Vietnam War movement with the NIH/NIMH Vietnam Moratorium Committee, and his worker support activities through the the Alliance for Labor and Community Action and the Alliance Unemployment Committee.
  - War moratorium committee, circa 1970-1971; Series 6 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Vietnam Moratorium Committee at NIH/NIMH, National Institutes of Health, National Institute of Mental Health, Rainbow Sign newsletter, Pete Seeger, Maryland Undeclared War Bill, Daniel Ellsberg testimonial dinner, Federal Employees for Peace
  - Alliance for Labor and Community Action, Circa 1976-1977; Series 6 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Alliance for Labor and Community Action, Action Newspaper, union support, Washington Post Pressmen Strike, Neisner's, Trailways, D.C. Health Coalition, Institute for Public Interest Representation at Georgetown University Law Center, Alliance for Labor and Community Action et al v. General Services Administration
  - Alliance for Labor and Community Action, Circa 1977; Series 6 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Alliance for Labor and Community Action, Action Newspaper, union support, hospital workers organizing, Say no to the FBI,
  - Alliance Unemployment Committee, Circa 1976-1977; Series 6 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Unemployment compensation, organizing the unemployed, full employment, unemployed councils, fight back,
  - Newspaper Group, 1976-1977; Series 6 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Newspaper study group, washington area labor and community newspaper
- Natasha Reatig papers, Circa 1969-2005; Circa 1969 - Circa 1975; Series 7
  Natasha Reatig was an active participant and leader in the Vietnam Moratorium Committee at NIH/NIMH, the Federal Employees for Peace and the League of Federal Voters, during the late 1960s and early 1970s, working to educate federal employees and mobilize them to help end the war in Vietnam.
  This series includes materials from Natasha Reatig's work with Federal employees to end the war in Vietnam during the late 1960s and early 1970s, including restrictions on free speech rights of employees by senior government officials.
  - Anti Vietnam War Activities, Circa 1971; Series 7 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Moratorium, Vietnam War, Vietnam Moratorium Committee at NIH/NIMH, National Institutes of Health, National Institute of Mental Health, Employee protest, Bond Bulletin, Daniel Ellsberg Testimonial Dinner, League of Federal Voters
  - Conflicts with Departmental Leadership, Circa 1970-1972; Series 7 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Employee protest, Suppression of free speech at HEW, HEW-52, HEW Caucus of Employee Groups, Elliot Richardson – HEW Secretary, Parklawn Building, The Condition of the Federal Employee
  - Newsletters, Circa 1969-1973; Series 7 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Keywords provided by the donor: fep newsletter, Rainbow Sign, Advocate
  - Miscellaneous, 1974; Series 7 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Tung oil supports
  - Anit-Vietnam war activites, 1971-1975, 2005; Series 7 (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Irv Riskin papers, 1975-1976; Series 8
  Irv Riskin was a union organizer, a McCarthy-era political witch-hunt victim, and a life-long activist for peace and social justice. His Washington area activities included leadership in the Gray Panthers and the Grape Boycott, and as a key Washington Post strike supporter, and mentor to a generation of social justice activists in Washington, D.C.
  This series includes materials from Irv Riskin's active involvement in the bitter Washington Post newspaper strike of 1975-1977.
  Related Materials
  Irv Riskin was a participant in the Lessons of the Sixties oral history project. The interview is part of collection MS2388. Listen to the interview.
  - Washington Post Strike [1/3], 1975-1976; Series 8 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Washington Post, strike, local 6 pressmen's union, Legal Defense Committee, Alliance for Labor and Community Action, flyers, clippings, newsletters
  - Washington Post Strike [2/3], 1975-1976; Series 8 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Keywords by the donor: Washington Post, strike, local 6 pressmen's union, Legal Defense Committee, Alliance for Labor and Community Action, flyers, clippings, newsletters
  - Washington Post Strike [3/3], 1975-1976; Series 8 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Fred Solowey papers, Circa 1970-1994; Series 9
  A native New Yorker, Fred Solowey has lived in Washington, DC since October, 1973. He worked full time coordinating the efforts of the Local Six Legal Defense Committee, during the Washington Post strike and its aftermath. Active in many organizations, he helped found and coordinated the Washington Area Labor Committee on Central America and the Caribbean and was the founding executive director of the Coalition to End Grand Jury Abuse. For the past 35 years he has been a labor journalist and editor for a number of unions.
  This series has materials covering many areas of Fred Solowey's activism in the early 1970s, including the campaign to impeach President Nixon, DC Statehood efforts, the DC Bank Campaign against redlining, DC labor activism, the community response to the murder of Yulanda Ward, the Citywide Housing Coalition, the McSurely V. McClellan court case challenging Congressional immunity for wrongdoing, and police brutality and the Terrence Johnson case in Prince George's County.
  - Impeachment - Nixon, Circa 1970; Series 9 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Keywords provied by the donor: Nixon, impeachment, Washington Area Impeachment Coalition
  - DC statehood Party Statehood, Circa 1970-1987; Series 9 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    Keywords provided by the donor: DC statehood, DC Statehood Party, Julius Hobson, New Columbia
  - DC Bank Campaign, Circa 1979-1981; Series 9 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Keywords provied by the donor: DC Bank Campaign, housing, Riggs Bank, redlining
  - National Lawyers Guild-DC Chapter, Circa 1977-1983; Series 9 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Keywords provided by the donor: David Rein, James Drew, National Lawyers Guild (NLG)
  - Washington Post strike [1/2], Circa 1976; Series 9 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Jim Dugan, Katherine Graham, Donald Graham, Washington Post Strike
  - Washington Post strike [2/2], Circa 1976; Series 9 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Washington Post strike sentencing and legal documents, 1977; Series 9 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Yulanda Ward, 1981; Series 9 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    Keywords provided by the donor: housing activism, Citywide Housing Coalition, murder/assassination of
  - Catholic Left, undated; Series 9 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Vietnam War protest, Mitch Snyder, Claire Marie, Steve Cleghorn, Community for Creative Non-Violence (CCNV)
  - McSurely case, Circa 1975; Series 9 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    Keywords provided by the donor: John McClellan, Al McSurely, Margaret McSurely, The New Yorker, Supreme Court
  - Strategic Communications Report, 1994; Series 9 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    Keywords provided by the donor: AFL-CIO, Strategic Communications Report
  - Terrence Johnson jury work, Circa 1981; Series 9 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Police brutality, Prince Georges County, Terrence Johnson, R. Kenneth Mundy, Brint Dillingham, J. Brinton Dillingham
  - DC Labor, Circa 1977; Series 9 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    Keywords provided by the donor: strikes, Evening Star, Washington Post strike, WHC, Washington, Grape Boycott, Source Collective
  - Housing DC, Circa 1979; Series 9 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Citywide Housing Coalition, gentrification, Al McSurely
  - Wilmington 10 Case, DC Gazette, Circa 1976; Series 9 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Wilmington 10 case, Rev. Ben Chavis, DC Gazette, same Smith, local political cartoons
- Roberta Spalter-Roth, Circa 1970-1974; Series 10
  Sociologist, founder of two women studies programs, research on class, race and gender.
  This series contains outline and drafts for Off Our Backs (oob) articles and other day to day information.
  Roberta Spalter-Roth was a participant in the Lessons of the Sixties oral history project. The interview is part of collection MS2388. Listen to the interview
  - Composition notebook, Circa 1970-1974; Series 10 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Notebook, Circa 1970-1974; Series 10 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Marcia Sprinkle-Kopit, 1967-1999; Series 11
  Marcia Sprinkle was influenced as a teenager by the civil rights movement, joined SNCC (Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee) while in college and moved to Washington, D.C. to continue her activism. She worked for many years as a community organizer, working primarily "across the color line" as a white person working in the black community.
  The materials in this series cover Marcia Sprinkle's involvement in the campaign in the late 1960s to establish a community-run school in the Adams Morgan neighborhood of Washington, D.C. Participants were parents, activists, teachers and other school personnel who were involved in that campaign. The papers also include her work with the Children's House day care program, which evolved from an unlicensed coop in the late 1960s to a fully licensed childcare center operating for 10 years. Participants were also active in pushing for the Brademas bill, the first legislation for national funding and standards for childcare subsequently vetoed by President Nixon as "socialist". They also spearheaded the work to create a childcare center at Georgetown Hospital and organized for childcare funding at the city level as well as providing childcare for a number of national organizations meeting in DC.
  - Morgan School [1/2], circa 1968; Series 11 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Antioch experiment, Washington Teachers Union, philosophy, elections, articles
  - Morgan School [2/2], circa 1968; Series 11 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    Keywords provided by the donor: covenant community, Community School Board, Hilda Mason 83rd birthday, letter to parents, budget, curriculum, adult classes, Bishop Marie Reed, teachers, grant from HEW
  - Morgan School, Circa 1967-1999; Series 11 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Children's House, Circa 1970-1991; Series 11 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Day Care Group, Children's House program, cartoon
- Alice Wolfson papers, Circa 1970-1980; Series 12
  Alice Wolfson is a veteran political activist and a pioneer in the women's health movement. She belonged to DC Women's Liberation, and was a member of "The Daughters of Lilith" collective. Hers was one of the leading voices protesting the lack of female participation in the 1970 Pill Hearings, as well as the deliberate withholding of information regarding oral contraceptives' dangerous side effects. Alice was one of the founders of the National Women's Health Network (NWHN) and organized many other actions during the NWHN's early years, including a sit-in in the office of the Secretary of the Department of Health, Education and Welfare, and the first FDA Protest. Alice served on the NWHN board of directors for several years. She also co-founded the Committee to Defend Reproductive Rights, which fought for and won both California state regulations protecting women against sterilization abuse and court decisions guaranteeing MediCal coverage of abortion. Today, Alice is a lawyer fighting for the rights of disabled individuals who have been discriminated against by their insurance companies.
  The materials in this series are from Alice Wolfson's activism and policy work in the reproductive rights movement.
  Keywords provided by the donor for this series: women's reproductive rights, women's health issues, 1970 US Senate hearings on birth control pills, abortion rights, scarf and picture of Alice Wolfson, feminism, lesbianism, "Old Mole," "Leviathan," CARASA—Committee for Abortion Rights and Against Sterilization Abuse, Ecology pamphlets, "Birth Control Handbook", "Rat", DC liberation pamphlets—"Dec 20, 1970 —10th anniversary of the NLF", Revolutionary Dynamics of Women's Liberation", April 1970 article in "Off Our Backs" on Alice Wolfson's experience on the David Suskind show, Sharon Wolfson pamphlet on women's liberation in junior high school, Roxanne Dunbar pamphlet, "Female Liberation as the basis for social revolution", Women's Liberation Center of Greater Hartford course materials for "Feminism, Socialism and Anti-Imperialsm: a course by and for women", Toronto Indochinese North American women's peace conference, "An Evaluation of the Canadian Conference process", Toronto, planning, Women Strike for Peace, third world women, Letter to Fourth World Women, Letter to Third World Women, Beverly Jones, Judith Brown, Gainesville, Fla. women's liberation, Women's Medical Center New York, NY board meeting minutes, National Library of Medicine Effects of Noise on Man, FDA Drug Bulletin, FDA investigation of IUDs, San Francisco Examiner Jan.29, 1978 article on "Alternatives to the Pill", 1971 Off Our Backs reprint, "Population Manipulation", 1971 Cornell University Program on Science, Technology and Society pamphlet by Andrea Parks Van Houweling on, "Contraception and Consumer Protection: The Fate of the Minipill", Statement by Roy Hertz, MD former Chief, National Institute of Child Health and Human Development - Reproduction Branch-"On the Pill and Carcinogenisis", Department of Health Education and Welfare-National Institutes of Health, "New England Journal of Medicine" article on "…Carcinoma Among Users of Conjugated Estrogens", January 1976 "Testimony Before the Senate Health Subcommittee" by William D. Finkle, Ph.D, Statement by Robert N. Hoover, MD. National Cancer Institute, "The Realities of Lesbianism" by Del Martin and Phyllis Lyon reprint from MOTIVE, news photos and clippings of 1970 Senate Pill Hearings, "Child and Family Reprint booklet-"The Medical Hazards of the Birth Control Pill", D.C. Women's Liberation Pamphlets, pamphlet by JANE and Chicago Women's Liberation—"Abortion — a woman's decision, a woman's right", 1969 Mobilization to End the War, Vietnamese Scarf, copy of news photo of Alice Wolfson, Student Nonviolent Coordination Committee pamphlet, "Double Jeopardy: To Be Black and Female" by Frances Beal, SNCC Black Women's Liberation Committee, "Women: A Journal of Liberation", antiwar movement, peace movement.
  Alice Wolfson was a participant in the Lessons of the Sixties oral history project. The interview is part of collection MS2388. Listen to the interview
  - Old Mole - collection of articles, Circa 1968-1970; Series 12 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Leviathan, 1970 May; Series 12 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Committee for Abortion Rights and Against sterialization Abuse (CARASA), 1978-1980; Series 12 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Ecology and Power Earth belongs to the people, 1970; Series 12 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Birth control handbook, 1970; Series 12 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Rat (newspaper) issue 19, February 3-20, no year; Series 12 (Box 14, Folder 7)